13亿人口
1.3 billion people.
飞速增长的经济
An economy that's surging.
越来越大的能源需求
More and more energy needs.
丰富的煤炭储量
Massive coal reserves.
中国北部的煤矿带
The coal belt in Northern China
- 内蒙古 - 嗯
-Inner Mongolia. -Right.
还有陕西省
Then there's Shaanxi province.
- 这里也有大型煤矿 - 就在这里
-And also biggest coal mine here. -Up here.
- 是的 - 露天煤矿？
-Yeah. -Now, is that an open pit mine?
是的……
-Yes. -Yes.
- 我每次去中国，接触到那些科学家 - ……露天煤矿
Every time I've visited China
- 都感觉中国也面临严峻考验 - ……不需要深挖
I've learned from their scientists. They're right on the cutting edge.
能不能给我个概念
Give me some sense of the numbers of
目前新建的火力发电站有多少
new coal fire generating plants.
数字十分惊人
Well, I have to say that the number is enormous
因为有巨大的利益驱动
because it's so profitable.
中国的问题同美国一样
This issue is really the same for China as it is for the US.
我们都使用陈旧、易污染的旧技术
We are both using old technologies that are dirty and polluting.
……越来越多的洪涝和干旱
...more flooding and more drought
还有越来越强的风暴
and stronger storms is going up
这一切都暗示着全球变暖
and global warming is implicated in the pattern.
要是请您给在座各位
And if you were to give some suggestions to everybody here
就目前的状况提出建议……
about, like, what we can do for the situation now.
分清真理和谬论
Separating the truth from the fiction
你们今天所学到的知识
and the accurate connections from the misunderstandings
就能帮助你分辨真伪
is part of what you learn here.
但当那些确凿的 有严密科学依据的忠告到来
But when the warnings are accurate and based on sound science
那么作为人类，不分国籍
then we as human beings, whatever country we live in
必须接受这样的忠告
have to find a way to make sure
然后作出应有的响应
that the warnings are heard and responded to.
我们为了废除「陋习」
We both have a hard time shaking loose the familiar patterns
都作出了艰苦的努力
that we've relied on in the past.
却面对着难以接受的结果
We both face completely unacceptable consequences.
我们正目击人类文明与地球的冲突
有三大因素促成了这一冲突
And there are three factors that are causing this collision
第一是人口
and the first is population.
我这代生于二战之后的「婴儿潮」
When my generation, the baby boom generation, was born after World War II
当时世界人口刚刚越过20亿
the population had just crossed the two billion mark.
现在我50多岁
Now, I'm in my 50s
世界人口已经达到65亿
and it's already gone to almost six and a half billion.
我要是能活到「婴儿潮」 这代人的平均寿命
And if I reach the demographic expectation for the baby boomers
这个数字会变成90亿
it'll go over nine billion.
人口增长用了10000代才达到20亿
So if it takes 10,000 generations to reach two billion
而在我们这一代
and then in one human lifetime, ours
就从20亿飙升到90亿
it goes from two billion to nine billion
同时引起了翻天覆地的变化
something profoundly different's going on right now.
地球的压力越来越大
We're putting more pressure on the Earth.
而且集中在那些贫困国家
Most of it's in the poorer nations of the world.
食品紧张
This puts pressure on food demand.
淡水紧张
It puts pressure on water demand.
脆弱的自然资源也受到威胁
It puts pressure on vulnerable natural resources
这也是为什么
and this pressure's one of the reasons
各地的植被遭受严重破坏
why we have seen all the devastation of the forest
不仅仅在雨林，各地都是
not only tropical, but elsewhere.
这是一个政治问题
It is a political issue.
左边一个政权 右边另一个政权
One set of policies here, another set of policies here.
破坏植被的不仅仅是砍伐 还有焚烧
Much of it comes not only because of cutting, but also burning.
每年30%的二氧化碳排放
Almost 30% of all the CO2 that goes up each year into the atmosphere
来自焚烧森林
comes from forest burning.
这是在6个月里 地球的夜间动态延时照片
This is a time-lapse picture of the Earth at night over a six-month period
城市的灯光是白色
showing the lights of the cities in white
红色则代表森林大火
and the burning forests and brush fires in red.
黄色代表煤气燃烧的火焰 像这里的西伯利亚
The yellow areas are the gas flares, like these in Siberia.
这样就引出了
And that brings me to the second factor
改变人与自然关系的第二大因素
that has transformed our relationship to the Earth.
科学和技术革命造福了全人类
The scientific and technological revolution is a great blessing
在诸如交通和医疗方面
in that it has given us tremendous benefits
给我们带来了诸多便利
in areas like medicine and communications.
但也赋予我们责任
But this new power that we have also brings a responsibility
去考虑可能造成的后果
to think about its consequences.
这里有个公式
Here's a formula to think about.
旧习惯结合旧技术 其结果可以预见
Old habits plus old technology have predictable consequences.
难以改变的旧习惯加上新技术
Old habits that are hard to change plus new technology
却会得到截然相反的结果
can have dramatically altered consequences.
刀光剑影的战争
Warfare with spears and bows and arrows
或者机枪火炮 这是一回事
and rifles and machine guns, that's one thing.
但当新技术出现
But then a new technology came.
我们则必须用新的眼光来看待战争
We have to think differently about war
因为新技术已经完全颠覆了
because the new technologies so completely transformed
过去战争的概念
the consequences of that old habit
因此我们不能 盲目地走过去的老路
that we can't just mindlessly continue the patterns of the past.
同样地，我们耕作以获取食物
In the same way, we have always exploited the Earth for sustenance.
大部分人类历史 我们都使用相对简单的工具
For most of our existence, we used relatively simple tools.
犁、拖拉机
The plow, the tractor.
但就是铲子 今天也大不同于过去
But even tools like shovels are different now.
这是以前的铲子
Shovel used to be this.
现在却要大得多
Shovels have gotten bigger.
每一年，它都越来越强大
And every year, they get more powerful.
所以在这个问题上 人类对地球表面的影响
So our ability to have an effect, in this case on the surface of the Earth
已经大不同于昨天
is utterly transformed.
你会认为对于灌溉来说 进步是件好事
You can say the same thing about irrigation, which is a great thing.
[ 科罗拉多河 ] 但要是我们不计后果地从河里抽水
But when we divert rivers without considering the consequences
河流也许再也没法流入大海
then sometimes rivers no longer reach the sea.
中亚有两条河
There were two rivers in Central Asia
曾经被苏联盲目地
that were used by the former Soviet Union
用来灌溉棉花田
for irrigating cotton fields unwisely.
咸海就是由它们汇成
The Aral Sea was fed by them.
它曾经是世界上第4大内陆海
It used to be the fourth largest inland sea in the world.
但我到那里时 看到了这幅奇怪的景象
When I went there, I saw this strange sight
一艘巨大的渔船停在沙漠里
of an enormous fishing fleet resting in the sand.
这是绝望的捕鱼业 面对消失的海岸线
This is the canal that the fishing industry desperately tried to build
开挖的沟渠
to get to the receding shoreline.
同自然打交道，稍有不慎
Making mistakes in our dealings with nature can have
就会酿成恶果
bigger consequences now
新技术规模上往往超出普通人
because our technologies are often bigger than the human scale.
把它们结合到一起 就能赋予我们强大的力量
When you put them all together, they've made us a force of nature.
这同样是一个政治问题
And this is also a political issue.
这是计算机绘制的世界地图
This is a computer map of the world
按照对全球变暖 影响力的比例绘制
that distorts to show the relative contributions to global warming.
我们国家的影响 等于整个南美洲
In our country, we are responsible for more than all of South America
加上非洲、中东
all of Africa, all of the Middle East
以及亚洲的总合
all of Asia, all combined.
这是非洲、印度、中国、日本 欧盟、俄罗斯的人均二氧化碳排放
The per capita average in Africa, India, China, Japan, EU, Russia.
还有我们的 远远超过其余几个
There's where we are. Way, way above everyone else.
要是乘上人口 情况稍有不同
If you take population into account, it's a little bit different.
中国和欧盟都有所增加
China's playing a bigger role, so is Europe.
但我们仍然是最大的「贡献者」
But we are still by all odds the largest contributor.
现在轮到我们来检视自己的看法了
And so it is up to us to look at how we think about it
因为这是第三个 也是最后一个
because our way of thinking is the third and final factor
改变人与自然关系的要素
that transforms our relationship to the Earth.
一只青蛙跳进沸水里
If a frog jumps into a pot of boiling water
会马上跳出来 因为它能感觉到危险
it jumps right out again because it senses the danger.
但同一只青蛙
But the very same frog
跳进冷水里
if it jumps into a pot of lukewarm water
然后慢慢加热到沸腾
that is slowly brought to a boil
它只会一动不动地呆在那里
will just sit there and it won't move.
就算温度不断升高 也不知道离开
It'll just sit there, even as the temperature continues to go up and up.
就一直这样，直到…… 直到被救出去
It'll stay there, until... Until it's rescued.
这只青蛙是得救起来
It's important to rescue the frog.
但转念一想呢
But the point is this.
我们大众意识和那只青蛙一样
Our collective nervous system is like that frog's nervous system.
对于突发危险有应急行为
It takes a sudden jolt sometimes before we become aware of a danger.
但若其逐渐变化，尽管速度飞快
If it seems gradual, even if it really is happening quickly
我们也会坐视不管
we're capable of just sitting there and not responding.
无动于衷
And not reacting.
在我童年的记忆里
I don't remember a time when I was a kid
没有哪个夏天 不是在忙碌的种植烟草中度过
when summertime didn't mean working with tobacco.
我……一度很喜欢这一切
It was just... I used to love it. It was during that period
同农场里的人们一起劳作
when working with the guys on the farm
十分开心
seemed like fun to me.
1964年卫生部公布报告
Starting in 1 964, with the Surgeon General's report
吸烟与肺癌
the evidence was laid out on the connection
被证实存在必然联系
between smoking cigarettes and lung cancer.
我们仍继续种植烟草
We kept growing tobacco.
Nancy比我大10岁
Nancy was almost 10 years older than me
我们俩总是在一起
and there were only the two of us.
她是我的保护神
She was my protector
也是我的好朋友
and my friend at the same time.
她从青年时开始吸烟
She started smoking when she was a teenager
从未间断
and never stopped.
最后死于肺癌
She died of lung cancer.
你绝不想那样死去
That's one of the ways you don't want to die.
一想到自己
The idea that we had been
作为这个经济现象的一分子
part of that economic pattern
生产香烟
that produced the cigarettes
也「生产」了癌症
that produced the cancer
简直……
it was so...
感到无比的痛苦
It was so painful on so many levels.
我那种了一辈子的烟草的父亲 从此没有再种
My father, he had grown tobacco all his life. He stopped.
过去任何变故
Whatever explanation
都没有能阻止他
had seemed to make sense in the past, just didn't cut it anymore.
这次却毅然收手
He stopped it.
顺藤摸瓜是人类天性 的确如此
It's just human nature to take time to connect the dots. I know that.
我知道总有一天 当人们期望更快地知道结果
But I also know that there can be a day of reckoning
就会回头重新审视整个过程
when you wish you had connected the dots more quickly.
有三大误区迷惑了大众
There are three misconceptions in particular that bedevil our thinking.
第一，科学界对于这个问题
First, isn't there a disagreement among scientists
是否还存在分歧
about whether the problem is real or not?
事实上，没有
Actually, not really.
曾有一项科学论文大型调查
There was a massive study of every scientific article
对象是过去10年里 所有关于全球变暖的专家评审文章
in a peer-reviewed journal written on global warming for the last 1 0 years.
做了10%的海量采样 共有928篇
And they took a big sample of 1 0%, 928 articles.
知不知道这里面 反对这一全球共识
And you know the number of those that disagreed with the scientific consensus
是人类引起全球变暖 或认为该问题无足轻重的有多少篇？
that we're causing global warming and that it's a serious problem?
所有的928篇里面 一篇也没有
Out of the 928, zero.
关于科学界存在分歧的谬论
The misconception that there's disagreement about the science
其实是一小撮人故意捏造的
has been deliberately created by a relatively small group of people.
有一份他们的内部文件泄露出来
One of their internal memos leaked.
报纸上是这样写的
And here's what it said, according to the press.
他们的目的就是 「将全球变暖」
Their objective is to reposition global warming
「重新定义为理论而不是事实」
as theory rather than fact.
[医生都爱抽「骆驼牌」 ] 这是陈年旧事了
This has happened before.
就在卫生部的报告公布以后
After the Surgeon General's report.
40年前的一份文件泄露出来 这是他们的话
One of their memos leaked 40 years ago. Here's what they said.
「公众的顾虑就是销量的保证」
"Doubt is our product
「这是迷惑大众最有力的切入点」
"since it is the best means of creating a controversy in the public's mind."
他们成功了吗？
But have they succeeded?
各位还记得那928篇专家评审的论文
You'll remember that there were 928 peer-reviewed articles.
没有一篇反对这一共识
Zero percent disagreed with the consensus.
这里是另一个面向大众读物的调查
There was another study of all the articles in the popular press.
在过去14年里 抽样调查了636篇
Over the last 1 4 years, they looked at a sample of 636.
一半以上的文章写
More than half of them said
「这个问题嘛，我不清楚 可能是也可能不是」
"Well, we're not sure. It could be a problem, may not be a problem."
怪不得我们会如此迷惑
So no wonder people are confused.
喂
Hey.
发现什么了？
What did you find out?
给谁工作？
Working for who?
主管？
Chief of Staff?
我要……
I'm gonna...
那是白宫环境办公室
That's the White House environment office.
美国石油协会 可以说那就是个游说团
American Petroleum Institute. It's fair to say that's the oil and gas lobby.
可以这样说吗？
Is that fair?
完全可以
Totally fair.
作进一步调查 看看他们的客户是谁
Do a little bit more and see who his clients were.
这么说他是 在为埃克森.瓦尔迪兹的船难辨护
So he was defending the Exxon Valdez thing.
很好 谢谢你
Uh, very. Thank you.
科学家有一个不容侵犯的职责
Scientists have an independent obligation
就是尊重他发现的真相 并公诸于众
to respect and present the truth as they see it.
为什么你关于这个问题的陈述
Why do you directly contradict yourself
会自相矛盾？
in the testimony you're giving about this scientific question?
文章最后一段不是我写的
The last paragraph in that section was not a paragraph which I wrote.
是别人加上去的
That was added to my testimony.
要是他们强迫你更改科学结论
If they force you to change a scientific conclusion
那就是他们进行学术造假
it's a form of science fraud by them.
前苏联强迫科学家
You know, in the Soviet Union, ordering scientists
篡改研究成功以取悦其政权
to change their studies to conform with the ideology...
我看到科学家们
I've seen scientists
[ 气象专家称NASA欲封其口 ] 遭到迫害
who were persecuted
受人奚落
ridiculed
丢了饭碗，失去经济来源
deprived of jobs, income
仅仅因为他们发现的
simply because the facts they discovered
是一个「不合时宜」的真相
led them to an inconvenient truth
他们却坚持要将其公诸于众
that they insisted on telling.
他在美国石油协会工作
He worked for the American Petroleum Institute.
2001年1月起
And in January of 2001
主持制定环境政策
he was put by the president in charge of environmental policy.
他收到美国环保署的一份文件
He received a memo from the EPA
警告全球变暖的问题
that warned about global warming
然后做了修改和批示 尽管他根本没有经过任何科学培训
and he edited. He has no scientific training whatsoever.
但他自作主张地反驳了科学家
But he took it upon himself to overrule the scientist.
我说 「我想瞻仰一下这位仁兄的书法」
I said, "I want to see what this guy's handwriting looks like."
这是环保署的原文 这些是他的笔迹
This is the memo from the EPA. These are his actual pen strokes.
他说： 「你不能这么说，纯粹就是猜测」
He says, "No, you can't say this. This is just speculation."
这是白宫的耻辱
This was embarrassing to the White House
所以这位仁兄几天之后就辞职了
so this fellow resigned a few days later.
而辞职当天 就投奔到埃克森.美孚门下
And the day after he resigned, he went to work for Exxon Mobil.
100年前 亚普顿.辛克莱写下了这段话
You know, more than 1 00 years ago, Upton Sinclair wrote this.
「要是给他发薪水的要他往东」
That it's difficult to get a man to understand something
「他怎么可能往西」
if his salary depends upon his not understanding it.
第二大误区
The second misconception.
经济和环境，就像鱼和熊掌 不可兼得
Do we have to choose between the economy and the environment?
这个问题很大
This is a big one.
很多人都这样认为
Lot of people say we do.
我曾劝说往届政府
I was trying to convince the previous administration
老布什政府 劝说其加入地球峰会
the first Bush administration, to go to the Earth Summit.
结果他们开了个白宫新闻发布会
And they organized a big White House conference
说「美国无需自降身价」
to say, "Oh, we're on top of this."
有一幅关于这个的漫画 引起了我的注意
And one of these view graphs caught my attention.
我想专门谈一谈
And I want to talk to you about it for a minute.
这就是我们面临的选择
Now here is the choice that we have to make
根据这些人的说法
according to this group.
天平的两端是不同的东西
We have here a scales that balances two different things.
一边放着金条
On one side, we have gold bars.
看上去不错吧
Don't they look good?
给我两块就知足了
I'd just like to have some of those gold bars.
天平的另一端呢 整个地球！
On the other side of the scales, the entire planet.
我认为不存在这样的选择 原因有二
I think this is a false choice for two reasons.
一，要是地球不存在了……
Number one, if we don't have a planet...
另一个原因是 如我们做得好
The other reason is that if we do the right thing
同样会带来滚滚财源
then we're gonna create a lot of wealth
- 还会带来更多的工作机会 - 说得对
-and we're gonna create a lot of jobs. -Yes.
正确的道路才能帮助我们前进
Because doing the right thing moves us forward.
这样的演说 我做了千百次
I've probably given this slide show 1,000 times.
准确地说，至少有1000次
I would say, at least 1,000 times.
从纳什维尔到诺克斯维尔 阿斯本、圣得西
Nashville to Knoxville to Aspen and Sundance.
洛杉矶、旧金山、 波特兰、明尼阿波斯
Los Angeles and San Francisco. Portland, Minneapolis.
波斯顿、纽哈芬、伦敦、布鲁塞尔 斯德哥尔摩、赫尔辛基
Boston, New Haven, London, Brussels, Stockholm, Helsinki
维也纳、慕尼黑、意大利、西班牙
Vienna, Munich, Italy and Spain
中国、韩国、日本
and China, South Korea, Japan.
谢谢
Thank you.
我认为自己在这个演讲上 投入空前的精力
I guess the thing I've spent more time on than anything else in this slide show
是想替人们清除
is trying to identify
那些思想上的顽石
all those things in people's minds
以便人们能理解这一切
that serve as obstacles to them understanding this.
无论何时我发现一块顽石
And whenever I feel like I've identified an obstacle
就会尽力将它打散、滚走、搬到一边
I try to take it apart, roll it away. Move it.
敲烂、炸得粉碎
Demolish it, blow it up.
我给自己定下一个目标
I set myself a goal.
要将这一观念清楚地传播下去
Communicate this real clearly.
我所知道的唯一办法
The only way I know to do it
就是一个城市一个城市
is city by city
一个人接一个人
person by person
挨家挨户地演讲
family by family.
- 再见，谢谢 - 再见
-Bye-bye. Thank you again. -Bye.
我坚信不久之后
And I have faith that pretty soon
唤醒足够多的人
enough minds are changed
我们就能迈过这个门坎
that we cross a threshold.
我来举例说明
Let me give you an example
错误地对待环境和经济平衡的后果
of the wrong way to balance the economy and the environment.
[ 温室气体排放标准 ] 其中一个与汽车相关
One part of this issue involves automobiles.
[ 温室气体排放标准 ] 日本的续驶里程在这一水平
Japan has mileage standards up here.
欧盟计划超过日本
Europe plans to pass Japan.
我们的盟国澳大利亚和加拿大 也把我们远远抛在后面
Our allies in Australia and Canada are leaving us behind.
这里是我们的标准
Here is where we are.
为什么会这样呢
Now there's a reason for it.
他们说美国不能太关注环境
They say that we can't protect the environment too much
以至于影响了经济 威胁到汽车制造商
without threatening the economy and threatening the automakers.
因为中国的汽车制造商 会跑进来蚕食我们的市场
Because automakers in China might come in and just steal all our markets.
而这是中国目前的续驶里程标准
Well, here is where China's auto mileage standards are now.
远比我们高
Way above ours.
我们没法买汽车给中国
We can't sell our cars in China today
因为没法达到中国的环境标准
because we don't meet the Chinese environmental standards.
加利福利亚已经做出一个创举
California has taken an initiative
规定其境内出售的汽车 要有更高的续驶里程
to have higher-mileage cars sold in California.
结果汽车商起诉加州政府
Now the auto companies have sued California
以阻止此项法律生效
to prevent this law from taking effect
因为他们宣称
because, as they point out, 1 1 years from now
这样就等于要求加州出售的汽车
this would mean that California would have to have cars for sale
11年后
that are as efficient 1 1 years from now
能达到中国目前的水平
as China's are today.
这要求简直太「高」了
Clearly too onerous a provision to comply with.
那我们的公司是不是业绩如虹呢？
And is this helping our companies succeed?
[ 市场占有率变化 ] 事实上 看看世界上谁做得最好
Well, actually, if you look at who's doing well in the world
是制造节能汽车的公司
it's the companies that are building more-efficient cars.
而我们的公司则陷入困境
And our companies are in deep trouble.
最后一大误区
Final misconception.
「就算承认这一问题的存在」
If we accept that this problem is real
「我们也无能为力了」
maybe it's just too big to do anything about.
很多人，从拒绝承认
And, you know, there are a lot of people who go straight from denial
径自走入绝望的阴影中
to despair
却不知道停下脚步
without pausing on the intermediate step
着手解决问题
of actually doing something about the problem.
这就是我最后想谈的 目前人们已知的
And that's what I'd like to finish with. The fact that we already know
能有效解决这一问题的方法
everything we need to know to effectively address this problem.
我们需要做大量的工作 而不仅仅局限于一件事
We've got to do a lot of things, not just one.
如果我们使用更节能的
If we use more efficient
家用电器
electricity appliances
就能减少这么多的污染排放
we can save this much off of the global warming pollution
这些原本都进入了大气
that would otherwise be put into the atmosphere.
要是采用别的节能设备 能减少这么多
If we use other end-use efficiency, this much.
拥有更多续驶里程的汽车 减少这么多
If we have higher mileage cars, this much.
还有更多，别的交通工具节能
And all these begin to add up. Other transport efficiency
可再生能源
renewable technology
碳固存技术……
carbon capture and sequestration.
还有更多的解决方案
A big solution that you're gonna be hearing a lot more about.
这些都加到一起
They all add up
我们很快就能将排放水平 降到1970年以下
and pretty soon we are below our 1 970 emissions.
各方面条件都齐备了
We have everything we need
我们还需要拯救我们的的政治意愿
save perhaps political will.
可不是？在美国 政治意愿就是可「再生」资源
But you know what? In America, political will is a renewable resource.
我们有这个能力
We have the ability to do this.
每个人都在引起全球变暖
Each one of us is a cause of global warming
但我们可以选择改变这一现状
but each of us can make choices to change that.
买的东西、用的电、开的车……
With the things we buy, the electricity we use, the cars we drive
我们可以选择 将个人二氧化碳排放降到0
we can make choices to bring our individual carbon emissions to zero.
解药就在你我手里
The solutions are in our hands.
我们只需要做出决定使其生效
We just have to have the determination to make them happen.
我们甘愿走在全世界的后面吗？
Are we gonna be left behind as the rest of the world moves forward?
那么多国家认同京都议定书
All of these nations have ratified Kyoto.
只有两个发达国家反对
There are only two advanced nations in the world that have not ratified Kyoto
我们是其中之一 另一个是澳大利亚
and we are one of them. The other is Australia.
幸运的是 很多州开始采取行动
Luckily, several states are taking the initiative.
北部9个州已经联合起来
The nine northeastern states have banded together
着手减少二氧化碳排放
on reducing CO2.
加州和俄勒冈已经行动起来
California and Oregon are taking the initiative.
宾夕法尼亚在利用 太阳能和风能上走在最前面
Pennsylvania's exercising leadership on solar power and wind power.
美国的各大城市也纷纷采取行动
And US cities are stepping up to the plate.
我们可以看到，一个个城市
One after the other, we have seen
〔支持京都议定书的城市〕 致力于解决全球变暖问题
all of these cities pledge to take on global warming.
那我们呢？
So what about the rest of us?
这个问题最终落实到一点
Ultimately this question comes down to this.
我们，作为美国公民
Are we, as Americans
有没有能力完成这一伟大义举
capable of doing great things
就算前方路途坎坷？
even though they are difficult?
我们有没有能力站起来
Are we capable
立于人类历史之上？
of rising above ourselves and above history?
过去的一切证明我们有这个能力
Well, the record indicates that we do have that capacity.
我们建立了一个国家 发起了一个革命
We formed a nation, we fought a revolution
还带来了新的创举
and brought something new to this Earth
一个保障个人独立的自由国家
a free nation guaranteeing individual liberty.
美国遵从道德的决定 否认了奴隶制
America made a moral decision. Its slavery was wrong
也不允许一半自由 一半奴役
and that we could not be half free and half slave.
我们美国人
We, as Americans, decided
决定女性应当享有选举权
that of course women should have the right to vote.
我们打败极权主义 同时在太平洋和大西洋
We defeated totalitarianism and won a war
获得了战争的胜利
in the Pacific and the Atlantic simultaneously.
我们在学校里废除了种族隔离
We desegregated our schools.
我们战胜了小儿麻痹症
And we cured fearsome diseases like polio.
登上了月球
We landed on the moon.
证明我们只要齐心 就没有什么不可能
The very example of what's possible when we are at our best.
我们国内两党联起手来
We worked together in a completely bipartisan way
推翻了共产主义
to bring down communism.
我们曾成功解决一大环境问题
We have even solved a global environmental crisis before
臭氧层空洞
the hole in the stratospheric ozone layer.
这曾被称为是不可能解决的
This was said to be an impossible problem to solve
因为它是全球性的环境问题
because it's a global environmental challenge
需要全世界国家连手解决
requiring cooperation from every nation in the world.
但我们成功了
But we took it on.
美国在淘汰有害化学物品上
And the United States took the lead in phasing out the chemicals
也走在世界的前列
that caused that problem.
因此我们需要 在政治上发扬民主主义
So now we have to use our political processes in our democracy
齐心协力共渡难关
and then decide to act together to solve those problems.
同时还要从全新的视角看待这一危机
But we have to have a different perspective on this one.
因为它绝不同于过去任何问题
It's different from any problem we have ever faced before.
记不记得那个地球自转的短片？
You remember that home movie of the Earth spinning in space?
其中一个飞船继续向外飞行
One of those spacecraft continuing on out into the universe
当它走到离地球40亿英里的地方
when it got four billion miles out in space
Carl Sagan说： 「让我们给地球再拍一张」
Carl Sagan said, "Let's take another picture of the Earth."
你看到那个淡蓝色的点了？
You see that pale blue dot?
这就是我们
That's us.
人类历史的一切
Everything that has ever happened in all of human history
都在这个小点上
has happened on that pixel.
所有的成功、失败
All the triumphs and all the tragedies.
所有的战争、饥荒
All the wars, all the famines.
所有的重大发展
All the major advances.
这就是我们唯一的家园
It's our only home.
如今它面临危机
And that is what is at stake.
危及到我们的生存
Our ability to live
on planet Earth
和人类文明的未来
to have a future as a civilization.
我坚信这是一个道德问题
I believe this is a moral issue.
是时候着手解决它了
It is your time to seize this issue.
人类要站起来，保护我们的未来
It is our time to rise again, to secure our future.
我今天所做的一切 没有什么特别的
There's nothing that unusual about what I'm doing with this.
不同的是，我在能年轻的时候
What is unusual is that I had the privilege to be shown it
就有幸能向人们展示这一切
as a young man.
女士们先生们 有请艾尔.高尔先生
Ladies and gentlemen, Mr. Al Gore.
像是开了一扇窗
It's almost as if a window was opened through which
而未来就在眼前
the future was very clearly visible.
「看到了吗？」他说 「你看到了吗？」
"See that?" he said, "See that?
「这就是你赖以生存的未来」
"That's the future in which you are going to live your life. "
我们的后代
Future generations
偶尔也会自问
may well have occasion to ask themselves
「我们的长辈们是怎么回事？」
"What were our parents thinking?
「在来得及的时候 为什么都不知道清醒」
"Why didn't they wake up when they had a chance?"
他们的问题，我们现在就应该想到
We have to hear that question from them, now.
正片还未结束 请耐心看完后面的内容
现在就改变生活，你准备好了吗？
气候危机可以解决
就从这里开始
访问 www.climatecrisis.net
你能减少你的二氧化碳排放
甚至减少到0
导  演 戴维斯.古根海姆
购买节能电器：比如节能灯泡
改进你的调温器：换成定时的 减少冷暖气的能耗
对房屋作节能评估 改进隔热性能
加强能源的循环利用
有能力的话 请购买混合动力汽车
多步行，或者骑自行车
乘坐轻轨或者地铁
告诉你的父母不要毁了你以后赖以生存的世界
如果你是家长 请与你的孩子一起
拯救他们以后赖以生存的世界
使用可再生能源
咨询当地能源公司 是否提供绿色能源
如果他们不提供，询问原因
选举致力于解决气候危机的领导人
上书国会
如不采纳 就参加国会竞选
植树：种很多很多树
到所在小区呼吁
参与电台热线、在报纸上宣传
坚决减少美国的二氧化碳排放
联合国际上的力量 阻止全球变暖
减少我们对进口石油的依赖
帮助农民种植醇类燃料作物
提高能源经济标准，减少汽车费气排放
如果你祷告
祈祷人类能拿出改变的勇气
《清醒吧》 词曲、演唱 玛莉萨.艾瑟里奇
非洲的古谚说
当你祈祷的时候，也同时采取行动
鼓励身边的人都来观看这部电影
尽可能了解气候危机的知识
然后把知识变成行动的力量